Guide to the Paul Robert Hanna Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Paul Robert Hanna Papers
1949-1970
SC0145
Hanna, Paul Robert, 1902-1988.
4 Linear feet (4 boxes)
Includes correspondence and notes concerning Stanford and the School of Education, Stanford Research Institute, the Jacks family fund, and other related issues.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Paul R. Hanna, 1975.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of Education at Stanford (1936-74; emeritus 1974-1988), Director of Stanford University Services (1942-44), Director of the Stanford International Development Education Center (SIDEC) (1963-68) and Senior Research Fellow at the Hoover Institution (1974-1988).
Paul Robert Hanna was born in Sioux City, Iowa, on June 21, 1902, to George Archibald and Regula Figi Hanna. Hanna spent most of his youth in Minnesota. He graduated high school in 1920 and married Jean Shuman in 1926. Paul and Jean Hanna had two sons and a daughter, John (born 1930), Emily (born 1932), and Robert (born 1934) and lived in the Hanna-Honeycomb House designed by Frank Lloyd Wright.
Throughout his school and college years, Hanna belonged to many organizations such as the Kappa Delta Rho, Student Council, and the Extemporaneous Team. He attended college from 1924 to 1929 to earn his Ph.D. degree which led him to become a teacher in Washington State University and in 1935 became an associate professor at Stanford University (Nelson). He had studied and taught elementary education, social studies, and he had improved the education of spelling as well as had his say in the international development of education. Additionally he consulted public schools and revised their curriculum. Paul R. Hanna had also a strong community relationship with his students and kept in contact with them long after they had graduated.
As an associate professor Hanna taught and developed a wide variety of courses. He advised on doctoral dissertations, founded the Stanford International Development Education Center (SIDEC), served on the Board of Trustees of Castilleja from 1957–1981, and worked as a senior researcher in the Hoover Institution in his last years to generate the Hanna Collection. Hanna wrote over eighty educational essays, sixteen books and several yearbooks before he died at age 85, on April 8, 1988.
Description of the Collection
Includes correspondence and notes concerning Stanford and the School of Education, Stanford Research Institute, the Jacks family fund, and other related issues.
Access Terms
Carnoy, Martin.; Carnoy, Martin.; Coladarci, Arthur.; Coladarci, Arthur.; Glover, Frederic O.; Glover, Frederic O.; Hanna, Paul Robert, 1902-1988.; Jacks, David, 1822-1909; Jacks, Margaret.; Jacks, Margaret; Moore, Frank.; Moore, Frank.; Quillen, Isaac James, 1909-; Schram, Wilbur.; Schramm, Wilbur, 1907-1987.; Shoup, Jack.; Shoup, Jack.; Sowards, G. Wesley.; Sowards, G. Wesley.; Stanford Research Institute.; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education.; Sterling, J. E. Wallace, (John Ewart Wallace), 1906-1985; Terman, Frederick Emmons, 1900-1982
Collection Contents
- Papers, 1949-1970
  - Stanford University - School of Education
    - Advanced Graduate Degrees, Committees on (CAGD) - Subcommittee on Doctoral Core Requirements, 1967 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alumni - Stanford Education Club of San Francisco, 1968 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - By-laws revision, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Coladarci, Arthur (Dean), general correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Comparative education, Committee on, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Convocation, 1962 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cubberly conference, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dissertation advising loads, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Elementary education, Committee on, 1967 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Faculty meetings, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Faculty meetings, 1965 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Faculty meetings, original and duplicates, 1965 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Faculty meetings, minutes, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Foundation executives meeting, 1963 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Hanna - reception, 1967 August (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Hanna - sabbatical leave, 1965 Winter and spring (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - International development education, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Jacks, David, Chair - Morris Rosenburg, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Jacks, Lee L. - Search meeting, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Jacks, Margaret, Chair - W.E. Lambert, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Joint appointment education and computer science, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous SUSE memoranda, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Peace Corps advisory board, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Policy committee, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Quillen, Dean (File #1), 1954 August-1959 September (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Quillen, Dean (File #2), 1959 October-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25a)
    - Quillen, Dean, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Quillen, Dean - Commes on, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Research and development center, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Research and publications, Committee on, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Research associates, Appt. of, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Research training program, Pre-Doctoral, Program Committee of, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Sabbatical leave and retirement chart, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - SIDEC (Stanford International Development Center), Advisory Committee to, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - SIDEC - Asian seminar, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - SIDEC - Carnoy, Martin, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - SIDEC - General correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - SIDEC - Moore, Frank, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Sociology/Education appointment, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Sowards, G. Wesley, 1955-1962 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Standing Committee - Lists, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Travel funds, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Visiting committee, 1966 November (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Stanford University - General
    - Academic council, Committees of the, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Advisory Board, Stanford, 1961 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Alumni office, Jack Shoup, 1949-1958 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Bookstore, Stanford, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Center in Hong Kong, Stanford, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Center in Japan, Stanford, proposed, Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Center in Japan, Stanford, correspondence, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence, general, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Executive Committee - Retirement policy, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Foreign students and visitors, Committee on - Subcommittee on curriculum enrichment, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Hoover Institution - Easton Rothwell, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - International studies, Committee on, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - International studies, Committee on - sample mailing for special meeting, 1958 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - International studies, Committee on - materials, duplicates, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - International studies, Committee on, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - International studies, Committee on, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - International studies, Committee on - minutes, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - International studies, Committee on, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - International studies, Committee on, 1964 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - The Stanford survey of the behavioral sciences; Report of the executive committee and staff, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Self-study - report and materials, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Asilomar, 1960 October 10 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - International studies, Committee on - Carmel conference, 1964 April 30-May 3 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - International studies, Committee on, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - International studies, Committee on, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - International studies, Committee on, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - International studies, Committee on, Report on foreign activities, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - International studies, Committee on, Policy matters re: AID/Stanford contracts, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - International studies, Committee on, 1963 September 1-1964 August 31 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Land and building development, Committee on, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Land and building development, Committee on, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - PACE - Faculty advisory committee for, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - PACE - Faculty advisory committee for, Meeting, 1964 April 7 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - PACE - Professional subcommittee meeting, 1964 March 5 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - PACE - Meeting, 1963 June 4 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - PACE - "A look toward Stanford's future." Final report, 1964 May (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - President-Provost, 1958 September 22-24 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - President-Provost - Frederick E. Terman, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - President's Office - Frederic O. Glover, 1956-1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - President's Office, 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - President's Office, J.E. Wallace Sterling, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Radio, television and motion pictures, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - ROTC (Shockley), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Schramm, Wilbur, 1955-1965 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - SRI (Stanford Research Institute), Taiwan contract, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - SRI, Taiwan project, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - SRI, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Tressider Memorial Union, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - UC - Kerr incident, clippings, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - University Policy, Committee on, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 28)